中字感谢YYeTs字幕组
翻译：珞珞珞小娘  薇薇安  盐湖凉白开
翻译：彼岸荼蘼  ShellyS  西查小鞋匠
校对：小酸奶 时轴：彼岸荼蘼 somehacker 麦旋风包
后期：8T  总监：somehacker  小酸奶
-= FRDS MNHD TEAM =-  wildcloudy@FRDS
有时候 我觉得自己受到了诅咒
Sometimes, I think I'm cursed.
因为在我出生前发生了一些事
Cause of something that happened before I was even born.
是这样 很久以前 我太奶奶的家里
See, a long time ago, there was this family.
他爸爸 是一位音乐家
The Papá, he was a musician.
一家人都喜欢唱歌跳舞
He and his family would sing and dance
过的很幸福
and count their blessings.
可是爸爸有个梦想
But he also had a dream.
让自己的歌声传遍整个世界
To play for the world.
有一天
And one day...
他背着吉他走了
he left with his guitar...
再也没有回来
and never returned.
我太奶奶
And my Mamá...
可没心情为离家出走的爸爸难过
She didn't have time to cry over that walk-away musician.
她把音乐彻底赶出了生活
After banishing all music from her life...
她要想办法赚钱养活女儿
she found a way to provide for her daughter.
她卷起袖子
She rolled up her sleeves...
学会了做鞋
and she learned to make shoes.
她明明可以做糖果
She could have made candy.
或者做烟花
O-o-or fireworks.
或者做亮闪闪的摔跤服
Or sparkly underwear for wrestlers.
可她就不
But no.
她选择做鞋子
She chose shoes.
后来她教会了她女儿做鞋子
Then she taught her daughter to make shoes.
再后来 她又教女婿做鞋
And later, she taught her son-in-law.
最后连孙子孙女们都做鞋
Then her grandkids got roped in.
人手越来越多 生意也越来越红火
As her family grew, so did the business.
音乐把这个家拆散了
Music have torn her family apart.
鞋子又把这个家凝聚在了一起
But shoes held them all together.
你看这个人
You see that woman...
这个就是太奶奶的妈妈
was my great-great-grandmother...
伊梅尔达
Mamá Imelda.
我还没出生时 她就过世了
She died way before I was born.
但是每年到了亡灵节
But my family still tells her story...
家里人都要把她的光辉事迹拿出来
every year on Día de los Muertos -- the Day of the Dead...
这个小女孩 就是我的太奶奶 她叫可可
And her little girl? She's my great-grandmother, Mamá Coco.
太奶奶 你好啊
Hola, Mamá Coco.
老头子 你来了
How are you, Julio?
实际上 我的名字叫米格
Actually, my name is Miguel.
太奶奶她记性不太好
Mamá Coco has trouble remembering things.
不过跟她聊天挺好的
But it's good to talk to her, anyway.
我基本上什么都跟她说
So, I tell her pretty much everything.
我以前是这样跑的
I used to run like this.
现在我是这样跑的 这样跑更快
But now I run like this, it's just way faster.
获胜者是 太奶奶!
The winner is... luchadora Coco!
我这边有个酒窝 这边没有
I have a dimple on this side, but not on this side.
有酒窝 没酒窝 有酒窝 没酒窝
Dimple, no dimple. Dimple, no dimple.
米格 好好吃饭
Miguel, eat your food.
这位是我奶奶 我太奶奶的女儿
My abuelita, she's Mamá Coco's daughter.
瞧 你瘦的跟猴似的 多吃点
Aw, you're a twig, mijo. Have some more.
够了 谢谢
No, gracias.
我问你要不要再吃几个玉米粉蒸肉卷呢
I asked if you would like more tamales.
吃..吃吧
S-Si?
我就知道你喜欢吃这个
That's what I thought you said!
我奶奶管理着这个家
Abuelita runs the house just as Mamá Imelda did.
不要音乐
No music!
就算要我付出..
♪ Aunque la vida... ♪
不要音乐
No music!
我觉得全墨西哥只有我们家不喜欢音乐了
I think we're the only family in Mexico who hates music.
我家人都觉得 没音乐也没啥问题
And my family's fine with that.
但是我
But me...
中午早点回来吃饭
Be back by lunch, mijo.
午饭前回来哦 米格
好的 妈妈
Love you, Mamá!
我可不像他们那样 我就是喜欢音乐
I'm not like the rest of my family.
- 早啊 米格 - 早上好
- Hola, Miguel. - Hola.
- 我拿一个 谢谢 - 拿吧 米格
- Muchas gracias! - De nada, Miguel!
嘿 丹丹
He-hey, Dante!
起来
Sit.
趴下
Down.
翻滚
Roll over.
摇一摇
Shake.
握拳
Fist bump.
聪明的丹丹
Good boy, Dante!
我知道 我不应该喜欢音乐的
I know, I'm not supposed to love music.
但这不能怪我
But it's not my fault.
要怪他
It's his.
歌神德拉库斯
Ernesto de la Cruz.
世界上最伟大的音乐家
The greatest musician of all time.
正是在这座广场上 年轻的德拉库斯
Here in this very plaza, the young Ernesto de la Cruz
迈出了他音乐事业的第一步
took his first steps toward becoming
最终成为了墨西哥历史上最受欢迎的歌手
the most beloved singer in Mexican history.
他最开始在圣塞西莉亚一点名气都没有
He started out a total nobody from Santa Cecilia, like me.
可他一开口唱歌
But when he played music,
人们就疯狂的迷上了他
he made people fall in love with him.
他还演过电影
He starred in movies.
他有最炫酷的吉他
He had the coolest guitar.
他还能飞
He could fly!
他写的歌也是最棒的
And he wrote the best songs.
但我最喜欢的一首是
But my all-time favorite is...
请记住我
♪ Remember me ♪
虽然我要与你们告别
♪ Though I have to say goodbye ♪
请记住我
♪ Remember me ♪
不要因此流泪
♪ Don't let it make you cry ♪
虽然我要离你远去
♪ For even if I'm far away ♪
你住在我心底
♪ I hold you in my heart ♪
在我们分别的每个夜晚
♪ I sing a secret song to you ♪
我都会偷偷为你唱一曲《请记住我》
♪ Each night we are apart Remember me ♪
虽然我要去远方
♪ Though I have to travel far ♪
请记住我
♪ Remember me ♪
当你每次听见悲伤的吉他曲
♪ Each time you hear a sad guitar ♪
我知道这是我与你在一起唯一的方法
♪ Know that I'm with you the only way that I can be... ♪
直到我再次拥抱你
♪ Until you're in my arms again ♪
他过着大家梦寐以求的生活
He lived the kind of life you dream about...
请记住我
♪ Remember me ♪
可惜在1942年
Until 1942.
一个掉下来的大钟把他砸死了
When he was crushed by a giant bell.
我就想成为他那样的人
I wanna be just like him.
有时候 我看着歌神
Sometimes, I look at de la Cruz...
我就有一种感觉
and I get this feeling.
好像我和他之间有某种联系
Like we're connected somehow.
我总觉得他能成为音乐家
Like if he could play music...
总有一天 我也可以
maybe someday, I could too!
要是家里人不拦着我就好了
If it wasn't for my family.
唉 你这孩子啊
Ay, ay, ay, muchacho!
啊?
Huh?
我让你擦鞋 不是听你叨叨家事
I asked for a shoe shine, not your life story.
哦 对 对不起
Oh, yeah, sorry.
在我们家里 我绝对不能提唱歌
I just can't really talk about any of this at home, so.
孩子 我要是你
Look, if I were you,
我就大声的跟家里人说
I'd march right up to my family and say,
嘿 我就想成为一名音乐家 你们要怎样
"Hey, I'm a musician. Deal with it!"
我可不敢这么说
I could never say that.
我只是唱给我自己听
I-I-I don't know.
你以前德拉库斯成名前
I mean, I only really play for myself.
天天藏着掖着
Ah! Did de la Cruz become the world's best musician
他那甜美的嗓音和演唱技巧么
by hiding his sweet, sweet skills?
不
No!
他经常去那个广场
He walked out onto that plaza
然后大声的唱出来
and he played out loud!
你看那边 他们在给今天晚上的
Mira, Mira, they're setting up for tonight.
亡灵节才艺大赛布置场地
The music competition for Día de Muertos.
你想像歌神一样么 就去报名啊
You wanna be like your hero? You should sign up!
啊 那我家里人会很生气的
Unh-unh. My family would freak!
你要是这么胆小 那就只好擦一辈子鞋了
Look, if you're too scared, then, well, have fun making shoes.
别怕 想想歌神是怎么说的
Come on, what did de la Cruz always say?
抓住你面前的机会
Seize your moment?
让我看看你的水平怎么样
Show me what you got, muchacho.
我当你的第一位听众
I'll be your first audience.
米格
Miguel!
啊
Ah!
奶奶
Abuelita!
你在这干什么呢
What are you doing here?
额..额..
Um... oh... uh...
你离我孙子远点
You leave my grandson alone!
你疯了吧 我刚刚只是在让他擦鞋
Doña, please! I was just getting a shine.
我知道你打的什么主意
I know your tricks, mariachi.
他刚才对你说什么了
What did he say to you?
他给我看了看他的吉他
He was just showing me his guitar.
真不要脸
Shame on you!
我的孙子就像一个
My grandson is a is a sweet little
可爱的小天使
angelito, perrito, cielito!
他可不想掺和你的什么音乐
He wants no part of your music, mariachi.
你离他远点
You keep away from him.
哦 我的小心肝
Ay, pobrecito!
刚才奶奶担心坏了
Estas bien, mijo.
你应该知道 不能来这种地方
You know better than to be here in this place.
你赶紧给我回家
You will come home. Now.
我们跟你说过多少次了
How many times have we told you?
那广场上全是些乱七八糟的人
That plaza is crawling with mariachis.
我知道 贝尔托叔叔
Yes, Tío Berto.
别别别
No, no, no, no, no.
快点给我滚 滚
Hey, go away, you. Go!
别打丹丹
It's just Dante.
不要给野狗取名字
Never name a street dog.
以后赶都赶不走
They'll follow you forever.
去 把我的鞋捡回来
Now, go get my shoe.
我又在那广场找到你儿子了
I found your son in Mariachi Plaza.
啊 米格?
Ay, Miguel?
你不是知道 奶奶不让你去那个广场么
You know how abuelita feels about the plaza.
我是去那擦鞋啊
I was just shining shoes.
给唱歌的擦鞋
A musician's shoes.
但是广场上的人很多啊
But the plaza's where the foot traffic is.
既然奶奶说了 不要去广场 那就不要去广场
If abuelita says, "No more plaza", then no more plaza.
那我今天晚上呢
But what about tonight?
今天晚上怎么了
What's tonight?
那个 他们要举办才艺大赛
Well, they're having this talent show.
- 我想我可以 - 报名?
- A-and I thought I might... - Sign up?
或许可以试试吧
Well, maybe?
你得有才艺 才能上台表演
You have to have talent to be in a talent show.
你有什么可以表演的呢 擦鞋子么
What are you gonna do? Shine shoes? Oh!
今天是亡灵节 都在家好好呆着
It's Día de los Muertos. No one's going any where.
今天晚上要和家人在一起
Tonight is about family.
你跟我来 干点正事
Ofrenda room. Vámonos.
别一脸不高兴的样子
Don't give me that look.
亡灵节是一年中
Día de los Muertos is the one night of the year
过世的亲人回来看望我们的日子
our ancestors can come visit us.
我们把他们的照片供奉在灵堂上
We put their photos on the ofrenda
他们的灵魂才能回来
so their spririts can cross over.
这可是非常重要的事
That is very important.
要是没把他们的照片供奉起来 他们就回不来了
If we don't put them up, they can't come.
我们做了这些好吃的
We made all this food.
摆上他们以前最喜欢的东西
Set out the things they loved in life, mijo.
都是为了能让他们回来和亲人们聚一聚
All this work to bring the family together.
你可别给我出去到处乱跑
I don't want you sneaking off to who-knows-where.
嗯?你要去哪
Huh! Where are you going?
- 我以为没我的事了 - 过来 孩子
- I thought we were done. - Ay, Dios mío.
我们是一家人 就应该待在一起
Being part of this family means being here for this family.
我可不想看到最后像那个...
I don't want to see you end up like...
像太奶奶的爸爸?
Like Mamá Coco's papá?
不许你提那个人
Never mention that man!
最好把他给我忘了
He's better off forgotten.
- 是你提的... - 嘘
- But you're the one who... - Eh, thchhsss!
- 我只是 - 嘘
- I was just... - Tchsshh!
- 但是.. - 嘘
- But... - Tchshh.
- 我.. - 嘘
- I... - Shhh.
爸爸
Papá?
爸爸回来了?
Papá is home?
妈妈 别着急 别着急
Mamá, cálmese, cálmese.
爸爸要回来了么
Papá is coming home?
不 妈妈 没事的 有我在
No, Mamá, it's okay. I'm here.
你是谁
Who are you?
唉 休息吧 妈妈
Ay... rest, Mamá.
我管你也是因为我爱你 米格
I'm hard on you because I care, Miguel.
米格
Miguel?
唉
Ay.
这孩子要拿他怎么办啊
What are we going to do with that boy?
哈哈哈 我知道了
Ha ha ha, you're right.
他需要的是这个
That's just what he needs.
啊
Huah!
是你啊 快进来
Oh, it's you. Get in here.
快点 丹丹 快点
Come on, Dante. Hurry up.
你可千万别给我找麻烦
You're gonna get me in trouble, boy.
别人会听见的
Someone can hear me.
要是有听众就好了
I wish someone wanted to hear me.
当然 是说除了你以外的听众
Other than you.
好了 好了
Ew, okay!
音调好了
Perfecto.
我一定要唱歌
I have to sing.
我一定要演奏
I have to play.
音乐不仅在我心里
The music, it's... it's not just in me.
音乐就是我的生命
It is me.
无论人生多么艰难
When life gets me down.
我会弹吉他
I play my guitar.
无论他们怎么劝我循规蹈矩
The rest of the world may follow the rules, but I...
我要顺从我的内心
must follow my heart.
啊
Ugh.
你有过那种
You know that feeling...
一首歌好像就是
like there's a song in the air
为你而唱的感觉么
and it's playing just for you?
心灵已相通
♪ A feeling so close ♪
伸手便可触及
♪ You could reach out and touch it ♪
我从没有感觉过
♪ I never knew ♪
自己如此的渴望
♪ I could want something so much ♪
这份感情
♪ But it's true ♪
你要有信心 修女
You must have faith, sister.
可是神父 他是不会听我的
Oh, but Padre, he will never listen.
那就用音乐来说服他
He will listen to music!
只有这歌 只有这歌
♪ Only a song, only a song ♪
才有能力改变你的心
♪ Has the power to change a heart ♪
永远都不要低估音乐的力量
Never underestimate the power of music.
神父
But my father,
但是他是绝对不会同意的
he will never give his permission.
我受够了征求别人的同意
I am done asking permission.
遇到好机会
When you see your moment,
决不能轻易放过
you mustn't let it pass you by.
你一定要抓住机会
You must seize it.
请问德拉库斯先生
Señor de la Cruz,
您是如何抓住了自己面前的机会呢?
what did it take for you to seize your moment?
我必须坚守我的梦想
I had to have faith in my dream.
成功不是靠别人施舍来的
No one was going to hand it to me.
我必须凭自己的努力去追逐梦想
It was up to me to reach for that dream.
坚持梦想
Grab it tight...
努力实现梦想
and make it come true.
我不会再躲躲藏藏了 丹丹
No more hiding, Dante.
我要去抓住机会
I gotta seize my moment.
今天晚上广场的才艺大赛 我一定要去
I'm gonna play in Mariachi Plaza if it kills me.
亡灵节的钟声敲响了
Día de Muertos has begun!
不不不
No, no, no, no, no.
我们要撒出一条路来
We have to make a clear path.
这些花瓣会指引祖先们回家
The petals guide our ancestors home.
- 妈妈 - 啊
- Mamá! - Hunh!
这张桌子要放在哪
Where should we put this table?
放到院子里
In the courtyard, mijos.
放到厨房外面么
You want it down by the kitchen?
对 跟另一张桌子摆在一起
Si, eh, next to the other one.
到下面去 躲到下面去
Get under, get under!
米格
Miguel?
没事
Uh, nothing.
妈妈 爸爸 我
Mamá, Papá, I...
米格 你的奶奶
Miguel, your abuelita have
刚刚提出了一个非常好的想法
the most wonderful idea.
我们决定好了
We've all decided...
是时候让你学做鞋啦
it's time you joined us in the workshop!
什么
What?
以后不用再去擦鞋了
No more shining shoes.
可以做鞋了 每天放学回来就能做
You will be making them, every day, after school.
噢 我奶奶最爱的小米格
Oh, our Miguelitititito
正好在亡灵节的这一天
carrying on the family tradition.
学习咱们的祖传手艺了
And on Día de los Muertos!
老祖宗们一定会为你感到骄傲的
Your ancestors would be so proud.
你可以像你维多利亚老奶奶那样 做凉鞋
You'll craft huaraches just like your Tía Victoria.
或者像你太爷爷胡里奥那样 做皮鞋
And wing tips just like your Papá Julio.
可是 我要是做不好怎么办呢
But what if I'm no good at making shoes?
米格
Ay, Miguel.
有这么一大家子人指导你呢
You have your family here to guide you.
你是咱里韦拉家的人
You are a Rivera.
咱们里韦拉家的人是干什么的
And a Rivera is?
都会做鞋
A shoemaker...
祖传的手艺
through and through.
真是我的好儿子!
That's my boy!
哈哈!大哥!今晚我们吃顿好的!
Haha! Berto! Break out the good stuff!
丹丹!
Dante!
不 丹丹 不能吃!
No, Dante, stop!
不 不 不 不 不!
Ah!
不
No, no, no, no, no!
德拉库斯的吉他?
No.
啊?
De la Cruz' guitar?
爸爸?
Papá?
可可太奶奶
Mamá Coco.
你的爸爸是歌神德拉库斯?
Is your papá Ernesto de la Cruz?
爸爸!爸爸!
Papá! Papá!
爸爸 爸爸!
Papá, Papá!
是他!
It's him!
我知道我的曾曾爷爷是谁了!
I know who my great-great-grandfather was!
米格 快从那下来
Miguel, get down from there.
妈妈 可可太奶奶的爸爸就是歌神德拉库斯!
Mamá Coco's father was Ernesto de la Cruz!
你到底在说什么?
What are you talking about?
我就要成为音乐家了!
I'm gonna be a musician!
这些都是什么?
What is all this?
你居然瞒着你的家人做这种事?
You keep secrets from your own family?
肯定是因为他经常跑去那个广场
It's all that time he spends in the plaza.
他的脑子里每天都是疯狂的幻想
Fills his head with crazy fantasies.
这不是幻想
It's not a fantasy.
这个人就是歌神德拉库斯
That man was Ernesto de la Cruz.
有史以来最伟大的音乐家
The greatest musician of all time.
我们根本就不知道这个人
We've never known anything about this man.
不管他是谁 他抛弃了家人
Or whoever he was, he still abandoned his family.
我的儿子绝对不能做这种事
It's no future for my son.
爸爸 你说过家人会是我的向导
Well, Papá, y-you said my family would guide me.
德拉库斯就是我的家人
Well, de la Cruz is my family.
那我就可以去做音乐
I'm supposed to play music.
不行!那个人的音乐对我们家就是祸害
Never! That man's music was a curse.
我绝不允许你碰音乐
I will not allow it.
- 只要你们... - 米格
- If you would just... - Miguel.
你必须听家里人的话
You will listen to your family.
不许再碰音乐
No more music.
只要听我弹一次就好
Just listen to me play.
讨论结束
End of argument.
你想像那个男人一样吗?
You want to end up like that man?
一样没有人记得?
Forgotten?
一样照片上不了家族灵坛吗?
Left off your family's ofrenda?
我才不在乎能不能上那个愚蠢的灵坛呢
I don't care if I'm on some stupid ofrenda.
- 不! - 妈妈!
- No! - Mamá!
好了
There.
吉他没了
No guitar.
音乐也没了
No music.
没事
Aw, come.
一家人吃个饭就什么都过去了
You'll feel better after you eat with your family.
这样的家我才不想要!
I don't wanna be in this family!
米格 米格!
Miguel, Miguel!
我 我想在广场上表演
I-I wanna play in the plaza.
就像德拉库斯那样
Like de la Cruz.
我 我还能报名吗?
C-can I still sign up?
你有乐器吗?
You got an instrument?
没有 不过如果我能借到一把吉他
No. But if I can borrow a guitar.
音乐家们必须要带自己的乐器登台
Musicians gotta bring their own instruments.
孩子 你找到吉他的话 我就把你加进名单
You find a guitar, kid, I'll put you on the list.
嗨 不好意思 我能借你的吉他吗?
Hey, excuse me, can I borrow your guitar?
抱歉 孩子
Sorry, muchaco.
你们有多余的吉他吗?
You guys have a spare guitar?
没有
No.
我想要借下你们的吉他 就一小会儿
I need a guitar just for a little bit.
一边去 小屁孩
Get outta here, kid.
曾曾爷爷
Great-great-grandfather.
我该怎么办?
What am I supposed to do?
不 不 不 不 丹丹 安静
No, no, no, no. Dante, stop.
别叫 安静
Cállate, shh.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
德拉库斯先生
Señor de la Cruz.
请不要生气
Please don't be mad.
我 我是米格
I-I'm Miguel.
您的曾曾孙子
Your great-great-grandson.
我 我需要借一下这个
I-I need to borrow this.
我们家认为音乐是不是好东西
Our family thinks music is a curse.
他们没有人理解我 但是我知道您会的
None of them understand. But I know you would have.
你会告诉我要顺从自己的心
You would have told me to follow my heart.
去抓住机会
To seize my moment.
所以 如果您不介意的话...
So, if it's all right with you...
我想去广场上表演
I'm gonna play in the Plaza.
就像您一样!
Just like you did!
怎么了?
What's going on?
有人偷了歌神的吉他
Somebody stole de la Cruz' guitar.
窗子被打破了 快看!
The window is broken, look!
是谁 谁在那?
All right, who's in there?
对不起 事情 事情不是你想的那样
I'm sorry, i-it's not what it looks like.
德拉库斯是我的...
De la Cruz is my...
里面没人!
There's nobody here!
- 米格! - 妈妈!
- Miguel! - Mamá!
米格 回家吧!
Miguel, come home!
天啊 孩子 你没事儿吧?
Dios mio, little boy! Are you okay?
来 让我帮你一把
Here, let me help you.
谢谢您 我...
Thanks. I...
你干什么?
Do you mind?
快看她都多大了
Look how big she's getting.
丹丹?
Uh! Dante?
你能看见我?
You can see me?
等等!这是怎么回事?
Wait! What's going on?
丹丹!丹丹!
Dante! Dante!
抱歉 对不起
Oh, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
米格?
Miguel?
- 米格? - 米格?
- Miguel? - Miguel?
你 你过来了!
Y-you're here!
你过来这边了
Here here.
你能看见我们?
And you can see us?
我们的小米格乖宝贝!
Our Miguelitititito!
介意告诉我你是谁吗?
Remind me how I know you?
我们都是你的家人啊 亲爱的
We're your family, mijo.
罗西塔姨奶奶?
Tía Rosita?
对
Si.
太爷爷胡里奥?
Papá Julio?
嗨!
Hola!
维多...利亚姨奶奶?
Tía Vic...toria?
他看起来不像是完全死了
He doesn't seem entirely dead.
但他看起来也不像是个活人
He's not quite alive, either.
我们去找伊梅尔达妈妈
We need Mamá Imelda.
她会知道该怎么做
She'll know how to fix this.
在这呢!
Oye!
伊梅尔达妈妈出事了!
It's Mamá Imelda!
她今晚过不来了!
She couldn't cross over!
她被拦住了!
She's stuck!
拦在那一边了!
On the other side!
奥斯卡舅爷爷?
Tío Oscar?
费利佩舅爷爷?
Tío Felipe?
嗨 米格
Oh, hey, Miguel.
我怎么感觉这件事跟你有点关系
I have a feeling this has something to do with you.
但是如果伊梅尔达妈妈今晚过不来...
But if Mamá Imelda can't come to us...
那我们就去那边找她!
Then we are going to her!
走吧!
- Whoa! - Vámonos!
来吧 米格 这 这没事的
Come on, Miguel, it's-it's okay.
丹丹?
Dante?
丹丹!
Dante!
丹丹 等一下!
Dante, wait up!
你得跟紧我 丹丹
You've gotta stay with me, boy.
你不知道...
You don't know...
这儿...
where...
这居然真的不是梦
This isn't a dream, then.
你们真的都在这儿
You're all really out there.
那你以为我们在哪?
You thought we weren't?
我也不知道
Oh, I don't know.
我以为这又是一个大人骗小孩的故事呢
I thought it might have been one of those made-up things...
就像大人们说的 说...
that adults tell kids, like...
多吃菜长得快
vitamins.
米格 多吃蔬菜就是有好处
Miguel, vitamins are a real thing.
好吧 我现在是有点相信了
Well, now I'm thinking maybe they could be.
宝贝儿 盯着人看不礼...
Mija, it's not nice to stare at...
啊我的上帝
Ay, Santa Ma...
那些是?
Are those?
吉祥物爱波瑞吉!
Alebrijes!
- 但是那些是... - 活的爱波瑞吉
- But those are... - Real alebrijes.
神奇的生物
Spirit creatures.
他们会给亡灵引路
They guide souls on their journey.
小心脚下 他们可是喜欢到处拉屎
Watch your step, they make cacitas everywhere.
欢迎回到亡灵之地
Welcome back to the Land of the Dead.
请准备好所有需要申报的物品
Please have all offerings ready for re-entry.
欢迎回来
Welcome back.
有需要申报的吗?
Anything to declare?
一些油条 家里人拿的
Some churros, from my family.
慢慢享用!
How wonderful!
如果您在入关时遇到困难...
If you're experiencing travel issues...
家庭团聚办理处可以
Agents at the Department of Family Reunion
为您提供帮助
are available to assist you.
下一个家庭
Next family, please.
两位的照片就在你们儿子家的灵坛上
Oh, your photos are in your son's ofrenda.
祝您旅途愉快
Have a great visit.
- 谢谢 - 谢谢
- Gracias. - Gracias.
请务必在日出前返回
And remember to return before sunrise.
祝您旅途愉快!
Enjoy your visit!
下一位?
Next?
您的照片摆在牙医家的灵坛上
Your photo's on your dentist's ofrenda.
祝您旅途愉快
Enjoy your visit.
非常感谢
Grashiash.
下一位?
Next?
是 就是我 大画家弗里达·卡罗
Yes, it is I, Frida Kahlo.
不用刷脸了吧?
Shall we skip the scanner?
我的照片摆在太多的灵坛上了
I'm on so many ofrendas
刷的话怕是会让你们的小机器过载死机呢
it will just overwhelm your blinky thingy.
哦 抱歉
Whoa, shoot.
看起来没有人供奉你的照片呢...
Looks like no one put up your photo...
弗里达?
Frida?
好吧 刚刚我说我是弗里达是吧
Okay, when I said I was Frida, just now...
刚刚
That.
其实我撒了个谎
That was a lie.
非常不好意思我道歉
And I apologize for doing that.
没有照片的话 就不能过桥
No photo on an ofrenda, no crossing the bridge.
这样吧?
You know what?
我神不知鬼不觉的过去 你就当没看见
I'm just gonna zip right over. You won't even know I'm gone.
就快...到了...
Almost... there...
就差...一点点...
Just a little... further...
给我起来
Upsy daisy.
好吧 好吧 算了 谁在乎这个?
Fine. Okay. Fine, who cares?
该死的花瓣桥!
Dumb flower bridge!
要是没人供奉我的照片我也没什么办法呢
Aw, I don't know what I'd do if no one put up my photo.
下一位?
Next?
快来亲爱的 到我们了
Oh, come mijo, it's our turn.
欢迎回来 朋友们
Welcome back, amigo.
有什么需要申报的吗?
Anything to declare?
其 其实我们还真的...
A-as a matter of fact...
有
Yes.
嗨
Hola.
Paging Marta Gonzalez Ramos...
Marta Gonzalez Ramos...
Please report to level seven.
好想念我的鼻子
I miss my nose.
拜托 帮帮忙吧 朋友
Come on, help us out, amigo.
我们今晚要去好多家呢
We gotta get to a dozen ofrendas tonight.
我们今晚才不会去你以前的老婆家过节
We are not visiting your ex-wife, Stanley,
想都别想
por Día de Muertos.
我要和管事的人说话
I demand to speak to the person in charge.
抱歉 女士 这上面说
I'm sorry, señora, it says here
真的没有人供奉你的照片
no one put up your photo.
我的家人每年 每年都会把我的照片摆在灵坛上
My family always, always put my photo up in the ofrenda
这个愚蠢的破盒子就是在撒谎
That devil box tells you nothing but lies.
伊梅尔达妈妈?
Mamá Imelda?
哦 我的孩子们
Oh, mi familia.
他们就是不让我过桥
They wouldn't let me cross the bridge.
快告诉这个女人和她的破盒子
Tell this woman and her devil box
我的照片一直就在灵坛上
that my photo is in the ofrenda.
那个 我 我们还没有看到灵坛
Well, w-we never made it to the ofrenda.
什么?
What?
我们遇到了...
We ran into a...
米格?
Hunh! Miguel?
曾曾奶奶
Mamá Imelda.
到底怎么回事?
What is going on?
你们都是里韦拉家的?
You the Rivera family?
是这样 你被诅咒了
Well, you're cursed.
什么?
What?
亡灵节是给亡灵们送东西的
Día de los Muertos is a night to give to the dead.
可是你居然偷东西
You stole from the dead.
可是我不是在偷那把吉他
But I wasn't sealing the guitar.
吉他?
Guitar?
那是我曾曾爷爷的
It was my great-great-grandfather's.
他肯定会把吉他借我的
He would have wanted me to have it.
停停停!不许提那个搞音乐的
Ah-ah-ah! We do not speak of that musician.
咱们家里早就当他死了
He is dead to this family.
那个 你们都死了啊
Uh, you're all dead.
阿嚏!
Achoo!
抱歉 这 这是谁的爱波瑞吉?
I am sorry, uh, who's alebrije is that?
这是丹丹
That's Dante.
他长得可真不像爱波瑞吉
He sure doesn't look like an alebrije.
他看起来就像一条普通的老狗
He just looks like a plain old dog.
或者说就像一根沾了几根头发的香肠也行
Or a sausage someone dropped in a barbershop.
不管他是什么 我 阿嚏!
Whatever he is, I am- achoo!
对他严重过敏
terribly allergic.
但是丹丹根本就没有毛
But Dante doesn't have any hair.
我还没有鼻子呢但是我就是过敏了
And I don't have a nose and yet here we are.
阿嚏!
Achoo!
你这都解释不了为什么就我过不去那座桥
But none of this explains why I couldn't cross over.
你把我的照片从灵坛上拿下来了?
You took my photo off the ofrenda?
这是个意外
It was an accident.
到底应该怎么把他送回去?
How do we send him back?
原来是家务事...
Well, since it's a family matter...
解除家庭诅咒的办法就是
The way to undo a family curse is
获得家人的祝福
to get your family's blessing.
就这样?
That's it?
得到了家人的祝福之后
Get your family's blessing
一切应该就会恢复原样
and everything should go back to normal.
但是你必须要在日出前搞定
But you've gotta do it by sunrise.
那如果是在日出以后呢?
What happens at sunrise?
我的天啊 你的手!
Híjole, your hand!
啊!
Huh!
米格 现在可不能晕
Whoa, Miguel. Can't have you fainting on us.
不过不用担心
But not to worry.
你全家人都在这
Your family is here.
你现在就可以获得祝福
You can get your blessing right now.
万寿菊花瓣 万寿菊花瓣
Cempasuchil, cempasuchil.
恕我失礼 夫人
Perdón, señora.
现在 你看着他说出他的名字
Now, you look at the living and say his name.
米格
Miguel.
就是这样
Nailed it.
现在说 我把祝福送给你
Now say, "I give you my blessing."
我把祝福送给你
I give you my blessing.
让你回家...
I give you my blessing to go home...
然后把我的照片放回到灵坛上...
To put my photo back on the ofrenda...
并且永远也不许碰音乐
And to never play music again.
什么?她不能这么做!
What? She can't do that!
理论上来说 只要她想的话 她就可以加条件
Well, technically, she can add any condition she wants.
好吧
Fine.
现在把花瓣交给他
Then you hand the petal to Miguel.
哈
Ha!
没有骷髅了
No skeletons.
马里亚奇广场 我来啦
Mariachi Plaza, here I come.
才过了两秒 你就忘了答应我什么了
Two seconds and you already break your promise.
这不公平 这是我的人生
This isn't fair, it's my life.
你们都活过一次了
You already had yours.
胡里奥太爷爷 我需要你的祝福
Papá Julio, I ask for your blessing.
罗西塔姨奶奶 你来?
Tía Rosita?
奥斯卡舅爷爷?
Oscar?
费利佩舅爷爷?
Felipe?
维多利亚姨奶奶?
Tía Victoria?
别把事情搞复杂了 我亲爱的孩子
Don't make this hard, mijo.
想回家就得听我的话
You go home my way, or no way.
你就这么讨厌音乐吗?
You really hate music that much?
我绝不能让你走曾曾爷爷的老路
I will not let you go down the same path he did.
曾曾爷爷的老路
The same path he did.
原来德拉库斯是我曾曾爷爷
He's family.
听伊梅尔达曾曾奶奶的话
Listen to your Mamá Imelda.
她是为了你好啊
She's just looking out for you.
要乖哦
Be reasonable.
抱歉 我要得去一下厕所
Con permiso, I need to visit the rest room.
马上回来
Be right back.
我们是不是得告诉他...
Ah, should we tell him
死灵国度没有厕所给他用
there are no restrooms in the Land of the Dead?
我们走
Vámonos.
有一家人正在找一个活着的小男孩
We got a family looking for a living boy.
我想成为一名音乐家 我需要一位音乐家的祝福
I wanna be a musician, I need a musician's blessing.
我们得找到我的曾曾爷爷
We gotta find my great-great-grandpa.
等一下 小朋友
Hold it, muchaco.
啊!
Huh!
我找到那个活人小男孩了!
I found that little boy!
各位 不好意思 让一让
Oh, excuse me. Excuse me, folks.
各位...
Excuse me.
啊
Oh.
丹丹
Dante.
扰乱公共秩序
Disturbing the peace.
拒捕
Fleeing an officer.
戴假一字眉
Falsifying a unibrow.
这也算犯法?
That's illegal?
当然算啦
Very illegal.
你得遵纪守法啊 朋友
You need to clean up your act, amigo.
朋友?
Amigo?
听您这么称呼我真是倍感欣慰
Oh, that's-that's so nice to hear you say that because
因为今年亡灵节我一直过得不顺
I have just had a really hard Día de Muertos
我现在正需要朋友伸出援手
and I could really use an amigo right now.
朋友之间 是会互相帮扶的吧
And amigos, they help their amigos.
我跟你讲 要是你能帮我今晚过桥
Listen, you get me across that bridge tonight...
我保证不会亏待你的
and I'll make it worth your while.
你是德拉库斯的粉丝?
You like de la Cruz?
我和他交情匪浅
He and I go way back.
我可以给你弄到几张他光芒万丈演唱会前排的座位
I can get you front row seats to his sunrise spectacular show.
我能给你带到后台 你能见到德拉库斯本人哦
I-I'll get you backstage. You can meet him.
你只要让我过桥就好
You just gotta let me cross that bridge.
我就该把你关到亡灵节结束
I should lock you up for the rest of the holiday.
我马上下班了
But my shift's almost up and...
我还想去看我活人世界的亲戚朋友呢
I wanna visit my living family.
所以我只给你个警告 你可以走了
So I'm letting you off with a warning.
至少把我的那一身戏服还给我吧?
Can I at least get my costume back?
啊...没门
Uh... no.
算什么朋友啊
Ser maldito.
嘿
Hey.
等下!
Hey!
你真的认识德拉库斯?
You really know de la Cruz?
谁会想....我去!你是个活人!
Who wants to... ah! Ay! You're alive!
是的 我是个活人
Yeah, I'm alive.
而我想回到活人世界
And I want to get back to the Land of the Living...
我需要德拉库斯的祝福
I need de la Cruz' blessing.
非得找他 这要求可真怪
That's weirdly specific.
因为他是我曾曾爷爷
He's my great-great-grandfather.
他是你曾曾 啥?
He's your gr-gr-gr- what?
恶心
Ew.
等一下 不对
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
等等
Wait, wait.
哈 我知道了!
Hunh!
等等 不对
Wait. No. Wait, wait, wait, wait
等一下
Wait, uh, wait,
等等
Wait, uh, wait, wait,
等等..
Wait, uh, wait, wait, wait,
Wait, uh, wait, wait, wait, wait,
等等..
Wait, uh, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait,
等等 等一下
Wait, uh, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait.
是啦!你说你是要回到活人世界去!
Yes! You're going back to the Land of the Living!
兴许问你就是个错误...
You know what? Maybe this isn't such a good...
不不 我能帮你
Niño, niño, I can help you.
你也能帮我 我们可以互相帮助
You can help me. We can help each other.
而最重要的是你能帮到我
But most importantly, you can help me.
-米格! 啊!
- Miguel! - Huh!
-我叫埃克托. - 很高兴认识你
- I'm Héctor. - That's nice.
等等我 小朋友!
Esperame, chamaco!
哎 这孩子会害死自己的
Ay! He is going to get himself killed!
我得找我的埃伯瑞吉来
I need my spirit guide...
佩皮塔
Pepita.
米格碰过的那个花瓣在这手里?
Who has that petal Miguel touched?
给你闻...乖乖阿尔布里奇
Here... n-nice alebrije.
嘿 别乱动
Hey, hey, hold still.
眼睛向上看 向上 对 向上
Look up, look up. A ver, a ver.
向上看
Look up, up, up!
好了
Okay.
大功告成!
Eh. Ta-da!
你跟真的死灵别无二致啦
Dead as a doorknob.
听好 米格 亡灵世界是靠活人记忆才得以运转
So listen, Miguel. This place runs on memories.
如果很多人记得你 人们会把你的照片供奉起来
When you're well remembered, people put up your photo...
这样你就可以在亡灵节期间过桥
and you get to cross the bridge
去探望你活着的亲朋好友
and visit the living on Día de Muertos.
除非你如我一般
Unless you're me.
你不能过桥?
You don't get to cross over?
没有人供奉我的照片
No one's ever put up my picture.
但是你能解决这个问题!
But you can change that!
这是你?
This is you?
对啊 长的帅吧?
Eh, Muy guapo, eh?
那你先到我去见我的曾曾爷爷
So, you get me to my great-great-grandpa...
然后我回家把你的照片供奉起来
Then I put up your photo when I get home?
你真聪明!
Such a smart boy!
对!这主意棒极了!
Yes! Great idea, yes!
不过有一点比较难 想见德拉库斯非常困难
One hiccup, de la Cruz is a tough guy to get to...
而我必须尽快过桥 今晚就得过去
and I need to cross that bridge soon. Like tonight.
所以我想知道你在这还有其他的家人吗?
So, you got any other family here, you know?
比较容易找到的那种 有吗?
Someone a bit more, eh, accessible?
呃 没有
Um... nope.
小子 你别想糊弄我
Don't yank my chain, chamaco.
你在这肯定有别的家人
You gotta have some other family.
只有德拉库斯
Only de la Cruz.
如果你不能帮我 那我自己去找他
If you can't help me, I'll find him myself.
好吧 好吧 小子 我帮你行了吧
Ugh. Okay, okay, kid. Fine, fine.
我带你去见你的曾曾爷爷
I'll get you to your great-great-grandpa.
找他可真的是很不容易
It's not gonna be easy, you know.
你知道 他可是..是非常忙的
You know, he's a- he's a busy man.
等等 你在干什么?
Wait, what are you doing?
我在学骷髅走路 我得融入亡灵世界
I'm walking like a skeleton. Blending in.
骷髅才不这么走路
No. Skeletons don't walk like that.
你不就这么走么
It's how you walk.
我才不是呢
No, I don't.
别学了!
Stop it!
哇哦!
Whoa!
德拉库斯的光芒万丈演唱会?
Ernesto de la Cruz' Sunrise Spectacular?
太棒了!
Que padre?
无聊 你曾曾爷爷每年都搞这么一出
Wuacch, every year, your great-great-grandpa
愚蠢的演唱会作为亡灵节的压轴戏
puts on that dumb show to mark the end of Día de Muertos.
那你能带我进去!
A-a-and you can get us in!
这个嘛...
I'm...
嘿 你之前可是说你有前排座位的票!
Hey, you said you had front-row tickets!
那个嘛..
That...
是我撒谎
that was a lie.
我对此表示歉意
I apologize for that.
放轻松 小伙子 来 我肯定能带你见到他
Cool off, chamaco, come on. I'll get you to him.
你有什么办法?
How?
因为我恰好知道他在哪排练
'Cause I happen to know where he's rehearsing.
呃
Ugh.
你最好把我的裙子带来了 埃克托
You better have my dress, Héctor.
你好啊 塞西
Hola, Ceci!
啊
Ay!
你好
Hola.
塞西
Cezi!
戏服我给弄丢了
I lost the dress.
我的天啊!
Ay, diosa Mia!
天亮前我得给40位舞蹈演员配好装扮
I've got to dress 40 dancers by sunrise.
- 现在因为你... - 塞西 塞西
- And thanks to you... - Cezi, Cezi...
- 现在我还差你这位舞蹈演员 - 塞西..
- I'm one Frida short - Cezi...
没法表演了 弗里达 - 丹丹
of an opening number. - Dante.
丹丹
Dante!
我们不能来这
We shouldn't be in here.
丹丹 快回来
Dante! Ven acá!
你!你是怎么进来的!
You! How did you get in here?
我只是跟着我的...
I-I just followed my...
哦 好可爱的无毛神犬
Hunh! Oh, the mighty Xolo dog!
游荡亡灵的指引者
Guider of wandering spirits.
你把谁的灵魂带到我这来了?
And whose spirit have you guided to me?
我觉着他不是埃伯瑞吉
I don't think he's a spirit guide.
那你就错了 死亡世界埃伯瑞吉可是形状各异的
Uh-uh-uh! The alebrijes of this world can take many forms.
他们既神秘又强大
They are as mysterious as they are powerful.
或许他就是条狗
Or maybe he's just a dog.
来 我需要你帮我看看
Come! I need your eyes.
你现在就是观众了
Your are the audience.
黑暗
Darkness!
而黑暗中的是..
And from the darkness...
一个巨大的木瓜!
A giant papaya!
舞者从木瓜中涌出
Dancers emerge from the papaya.
这些舞者..
And the dancers...
全都是我!
Are all me!
他们去吸吮仙人掌母亲的乳汁
And they go to drink from the milk of their mother.
这个仙人掌也是我!
Who is a cactus. But who is also me!
而她的乳汁却不是乳汁
And her milk is not milk...
而是眼泪
but tears.
是不是太夸张了?
Is it too obvious?
我觉着夸张程度把握的相当准确
I think it's just the right amount of obvious.
可以配上点音乐
It could use some music.
哦 比如你可以这样...
Oh, what if you did like...
嘟-嘟-嘟-嘟-嘟?
Tun-tun-tun-tun-tun?
哦 然后再这样...
Oh, and then it could go...
哒啦啦-哒啦啦-哒啦啦-哒啦啦 嘟?
Darala-dalala-dalala-dalala Whenk?
那在舞台上布满熊熊烈火如何?
And what if everything was on fire?
对 熊熊烈火!
Yes! Fire everywhere!
灵感井喷!
Inspired.
你是个天生的艺术家
You. You have the spirit of an artist.
舞者退场 音乐淡出 灯光关闭
The dancers exit. The music fades. The lights go out.
然后德拉库斯升上舞台中央
And Ernesto de la Cruz rises to the stage.
啊?
Huh?
他唱几首歌 太阳升起 观众们欢呼雀跃
He does a couple of songs. The sun rises. Everyone cheers.
冒昧问一下 德拉库斯本人现在何处?
Excuse me, where's the real de la Cruz?
他从来不彩排
Ernesto doesn't do rehearsals.
他在自己的塔顶忙着喝酒聚会呢
He's too busy hosting that fancy party at the top of his tower.
小子 你不能到处乱跑
Chamaco, you can't run off on me like that.
来吧 别打扰这些大明星了
Come on, stop pestering the celebrities.
你说我的曾曾爷爷会在这
You said my great-great-grandpa would be here.
他明明在亡灵城的那一边举办派对呢
He's halfway across town throwing some big party.
那个混蛋 自己的演唱会都不来排练?
That bum. Who doesn't show up to his own rehearsal?
如果你跟他交情匪浅 为什么他没邀请你去派对呢?
If you're such good friends, how come he didn't invite you?
他还是你曾曾爷爷呢 他怎么不邀请你?
He's your great-great-grandpa. How come he didn't invite you?
嘿 古斯塔沃!那边的派对你知道是怎么回事吗?
Hey, Gustavo! You know anything about this party?
一票难求!
Sh-it's the hot ticket!
如果你不在邀请名单里的话 你就别想进去
But if you're not on the guest list, you're never gettin' in,
腊香肠
Chorizo.
嘿 是腊香肠
Hey, it's Chorizo!
呵呵 很好笑 非常好笑
Ah-ha, very funny, guys. Very funny.
腊香肠?
Chorizo?
哦 这家伙可出名了
Oh, this guy's famous.
快啊 你问问他是怎么死的
Go on, go on. Ask him how he died.
我不想提起那件事
I-I don't wanna talk about it.
他是吃腊香肠噎死的!
He choked on some chorizo!
我不是噎死的 好吧?是食物中毒
I didn't choke, okay? I got food poisoning
区别很大的
which is a big difference.
所以说我讨厌搞音乐的
This is why I don't like musicians.
一群自以为是的混蛋!
Bunch of self-important jerks!
嘿 我也是个搞音乐的好吧
Hey, I'm a musician.
-你也是? - 那个..
- You are? - Well...
如果你真想参加那个派对去见德拉库斯
If you really wanna get to Ernesto...
德拉库斯广场有个音乐才艺比赛
there is that music competition at the Plaza de la Cruz.
获胜者可以在派对里表演才艺
Winner gets to play at his party.
不 不 小伙子 你可别抽风想去参加...
No, no, no, Chamaco! You are loco if you think...
我必须得到我曾曾爷爷的祝福
I need to get my great-great- grandfather's blessing.
你知道哪能搞到一把吉他吗?
You know where I can get a guitar?
哎 我倒是认识个人
Ay... I know a guy.
你找到他了吗 佩皮塔?你找到米格了吗?
Have you found him, Pepita? Have you found our boy?
一个脚印!
A footprint!
是我们家的鞋
It's a Rivera boot.
- 7码的鞋 - 是7码半
- Size seven! - And a half.
- 内八字 - 是米格
- Pronated. - Miguel.
你到底是怎么想的 居然想搞音乐?
Why the heck would you wanna be a musician?
我曾曾爷爷是个音乐家
My great-great-grandfather's a musician.
谁会愿意一生都像个猴子似的为一群陌生人表演音乐?
Who spent his life performing like a monkey for complete strangers?
搞不懂!我可理解不了
Blech! No, no, thank you, no.
你知道什么啊?
What do you know?
你说的那把吉他还得走多久才能找到?
So, how far is this guitar, anyway?
马上就到了
We're almost there.
跟上啊 小子
Keep up, chamaco, come on!
埃克托表弟
Cousin Héctor!
嘿 是你们啊!
Hey! These guys!
埃克托!
Héctor!
嘿 舅舅 你好吗?
Hey, tío, qué onda?
这些人都是你的亲人?
These people are all you family?
呃..算是吧
Eh... yeah, in a way.
我们这些人都没有灵坛或者照片被人供奉起来
We're all the ones with no photos or ofrendas.
没有可以去看的家人
No family to go home to.
几乎被人彻底遗忘了 你懂吧?
Nearly forgotten, you know?
所以我们就互相认了亲 我叫你表哥 他叫我舅舅之类的
So we all call each other "cousin" or "tío" or-or whatever.
- 埃克托! - 雪洛姨妈 嘿!
- Héctor! - Tía Chelos! Hey!
非常感谢
Muchas gracias.
给我留点
Save some for me.
猪皮哥在吗?
Is Chicharrón around?
他在小屋里 我想他好像不太想见外人
In the bungalow. I don't know if he's in the mood for visitors.
谁会不想见我埃克托啊?
Ah, who doesn't like a visit from cousin Héctor?
啊!
Huh!
晚上好啊 猪皮哥
Buenas noches, Chicharrón.
我可不想见你这张蠢脸 埃克托
I don't want to see your stupid face, Héctor.
别这样 今天可是亡灵节
Come on, its Día de Muertos.
我带点儿酒跟你喝两口
I brought you a little offering.
你给我出去!
Get outta here!
我可以马上就走 不过嘛..
I would Chich, but the thing is...
我和我的小朋友米格
me and my friend Miguel...
很想借你的吉他用用
we really need to borrow your guitar.
- 我的吉他? - 是啊
- My guitar? - Yes.
我珍爱的宝贝吉他?
My prized, beloved guitar?
我保证用完肯定还给你
I promise we'll bring it right back.
像你之前保证还给我的小货车那样吗?
Like the time you promised to bring back my van?
呃...
Eh...
- 还有我的小冰箱? - 哦 我说..
- Or my mini fridge? - Oh, you see...
我的手帕 我的绳子 我的大腿骨?
Or my good napkins, my lasso, my femur?!
不不 这回跟之前不一样
No, not like those things.
我的大腿骨呢 你这...
Where's my femur, you...
哦..哦..
Oh, oh.
你还好吗 老伙计?
You okay, amigo?
我要不行了 埃克托
I'm fading, Héctor.
我能感觉得到
I can feel it.
就算我现在想弹吉他我也弹不动了
I couldn't even play that thing if I wanted to.
你给我弹点什么吧
You, play me something.
不 你知道我再也不弹吉他了的 猪皮哥
Oh, you know I don't play anymore, Chich.
吉他是给那小男孩用的
The guitar's for the kid.
你想借用我的吉他?
You want it?
你必须给我弹一曲
You've got to earn it.
哎 那就为你破例一次吧 老伙计
Ay, only for you, amigo.
你想听什么?
Any requests?
你知道我最爱听哪首歌 埃克托
You know my favorite, Héctor.
谁都知道胡安妮塔
♪ Well, everyone knows Juanita ♪
他瞳孔有不同颜色
♪ Her eyes each a different color ♪
牙齿又歪
♪ Her teeth stick out ♪
面颊又塌下
♪ And her chin goes in ♪
而她长长的
♪ And her... ♪
手关节拖到了地上
♪ Knuckles they drag on the floor ♪
你歌词唱错了
Those aren't the words.
这还有小孩子呢
There are children present.
头发像荆棘一样
♪ Her hair is like a brier ♪
站着总是两腿弯弯
♪ She stands in a bow-legged stance ♪
要不是我奇丑无比
♪ And if I weren't so ugly ♪
她或许会留意我
♪ She'd possibly give me a chance ♪
想起来不少往事
Brings back memories.
多谢了
Gracias.
他 他怎么啦?
Wait, what happened?
被人遗忘了
He's been forgotten.
如果在那边的活人世界里没人记得你
When there's no one left in the living world who remembers you...
这边的你就会消失
you disappear from this world.
我们将这称作"终极死亡"
We call it "The Final Death."
那 那它去哪儿啦?
W-where did he go?
无人知晓啊
No one knows.
但是我见过他啊
But I've met him.
我回去的时候我还记得它啊
I could remember him... when I go back.
不是你想的那样 孩子
No, it doesn't work like that, chamaco.
我们的故事
Our memories...
只能由我们生前的认识的那些人来讲
They have to be passed down by those who knew us in life.
他们的记忆才管用
In the stories they tell about us.
但是活人的世界里没人记得猪皮哥了
But there's no one left alive to pass down Chich's stories.
嘿 谁都有消失的一天
Hey, it happens to everyone eventually.
走吧 未来的歌神 你还要去比赛呢
Come on, de la Cruzito, you've got a contest to win.
你还说你讨厌搞音乐
You told me you hated musicians.
想不到你自己就是一个音乐家
You never said you were one.
你知道我是怎么认识你曾曾爷爷的?
How do you think I knew your great-great-grandpa?
我们一直是搭档
We used to play music together.
他的本事都是我教的
Taught him everything he knows.
你可别吹牛了?
No manches.
你是德拉库斯的搭档?
You played with Ernesto de la Cruz?
他可是当今世界上最伟大的音乐家!
The greatest musician of all time?
你可真搞笑
Oh! Oh, you're funny.
它的眉毛也许可以夸夸
Greatest eyebrows of all time, maybe.
但他的音乐 您还是别提了
But his music, eh, not so much.
你吹牛吹得可太过分了
You don't know what you're talking about.
欢迎来到德拉库斯广场
Welcome to the Plaza de la Cruz.
好好表现 米格
Showtime, chamaco.
走过路过千万不要错过 文化衫!
Querer lo, t-shirts, bobbleheads.
各位晚上好
Bienvenidos a todos!
你们都准备好了吗?
Who's ready for some música?
这是一场音乐大战
It's a Battle of the Bands, amigos.
获胜者将在今晚参加歌神德拉库斯的
The winner gets to play for the maestro himself...
盛大晚宴 就在那座高塔上
Ernesto de la Cruz on his fiesta tonight!
这场比赛就是我们的入场券 孩子们
That's our ticket, muchacho.
比赛现在开始
Let the competition begin!
什么情况?你准备唱什么?
So, what's the plan? W-what are you gonna play?
当然是"请记住我"了
Definitely "Remember Me."
不 不能唱这首
No, not that one. No.
怎么啦?那可是他最热门的歌
Come on, it's the most popular song.
太俗了
Ah, it's too popular.
虽然我要去远方
♪ Remember me though I have to travel far ♪
请记住我
♪ Remember... ♪
眼泪不要坠落
♪ Don't let it make you cry ♪
那我唱有点疯狂怎么样?
Um, what about... Poco Loco?
对!这首就对了!
Epa! Now, that's a song.
未来歌神 你做好准备
De la Cruzito! You're on standby.
鹏鹏恰恰 你准备上台
Los Chachalacos, you're up next.
鹏鹏恰恰!
Los Chachalacos!
你每次上台前都这么紧张吗?
You always this nervous before a performance?
我不知道 这是我第一次上台表演
I don't know. I've never performed before.
什么?你不是搞音乐的吗?
What? You said you were a musician!
我是啊 我的意思是 等我赢了
I am! I mean, I-I will be.
我天 一旦我赢了
- Ay! - Once I win.
这就是你的计划?
That's your plan?
不不 你必须得赢 米格
No, no, no, no. You have to win, Miguel.
你要是赢不了 就没命了
Your life literally depends on you winning.
你以前没上台表演过?
And you've never done this before?
- 还是我上吧 - 别别别
- I'll go up. - Uh, n-no!
- 我一定要自己上 - 为什么?
- I need to do this. - Why?
如果我连上台表演都不敢
If I can't go out there and play one song...
那我还当什么音乐家啊?
how can I call myself a musician?
这有什么关系?
What does that matter?
当然有了 因为我不仅想要得到歌神的祝福
'Cause I don't just want to get de la Cruz' blessing.
我还要证明
I need to prove that...
我值得他的祝福
that I'm worthy of it.
天哪 多么感人的想法啊
Oh. Oh, that's such a sweet sentiment.
但却偏偏在这个时候
At such a bad time!
好吧 好吧 好吧 好吧
Okay! Okay, okay. Okay.
如果你想上台表演 那就给我好好的演
Okay, you wanna perform? Then you've got to perform!
首先 要全身放松
First, you have to loosen up.
把紧张抖掉
Shake off those nerves.
现在跟我一起放声长啸
Now, give me your best grito.
什么是放声长啸?
My best grito?
就是这样 玩命的嚎叫
Come on, yell. Belt it out.
感觉不错
Oh, it feels good.
好 现在轮到你了
Okay, now, now, now you.
哎 死定了 孩子
Oh, come on, kid.
未来歌神 该你上了
De la Cruzito! You're on now!
米格 看着我 嗨 米格看着我
Miguel, look at me. Hey, hey, look at me.
快点!该上场了!
Come on, let's go!
你没问题的
You can do this.
放松 别紧张
Grab their attention and don't let it go!
埃克托
Héctor...
米格 你最棒 没问题的
Make them listen, chamaco. You've got this.
欢迎未来歌神
De la Cruzito!
嘿 你最棒了
Arriba-Ba! Hey!
他在干什么?他怎么不唱啊?
What's he doing? Why isn't he playing?
不唱你就滚回去
Bring back the singing dog!
天空是什么颜色?
♪ What color is the sky? ♪
亲爱的 亲爱的
♪ Ay, mi amor, ay, mi amor ♪
你说它是红色
♪ You tell me that it's red ♪
亲爱的 亲爱的
♪ Ay, mi amor, ay, mi amor ♪
鞋放在哪儿呢?
♪ Where should I put my shoes? ♪
亲爱的 亲爱的
♪ Ay, mi amor, ay, mi amor ♪
你说 放在你头上吧
♪ You say, "put them on your head!" ♪
亲爱的 亲爱的
♪ Ay, mi amor, ay, mi amor ♪
你让我疯狂
♪ You make me un poco loco ♪
你让我着迷
♪ un poquititito loco ♪
这是怎么了?
♪ The way you keep me guessing ♪
我点头 我同意
♪ I'm nodding and I'm yesing ♪
这是我的福气
♪ I'll count it as a blessing ♪
我不过是有一点疯狂
♪ That I'm only un poco loco ♪
跳得不错 老骨头
Not bad for a dead guy.
你唱得也不错啊 小肥仔
Not so bad yourself, gordito.
来吧
Eso!
就在附近 去找他
He's close. Find him.
这疯狂由你开始
♪ The loco that you make me ♪
这实在是疯狂无比
♪ It is just un poco crazy ♪
你真的非常无理
♪ The sense that you're not making ♪
你管我
♪ The liberties you're taking ♪
让我摇摇头叹息
♪ Leaves my cabeza shaking ♪
你就是有一点疯狂
♪ You are just un poco loco ♪
冠军就是 米格!
Numero uno, Miguelito!
我们正在找一个活人小男孩
We're looking for a living kid.
十二岁左右
About twelve?
你们见没见到一个活人小男孩?
Have you seen a living boy?
有一点点点点点点点点
♪ Un poquiti-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti-ti ♪
点点点点点疯狂
♪ ti-ti-ti-ti-to loco! ♪
嗨 你做到了!
Hey! You did good!
我真为你骄傲
I'm proud of you.
好!
Eso!
喂 你要去哪儿啊?
Hey, where are you going?
我们快点离开这儿
We gotta get outta here.
什么!你疯啦!我们这就快要赢了!
What? You're crazy! We're about to win this thing.
女士们 先生们 安静
Damas y caballeros...
我刚收到一条紧急通知
I have a emergency announcement.
请大家帮忙找一位活人小男孩
Please be on the look out for a living boy.
他的名字叫米格
Answers to the name of Miguel.
今晚早些时候 他从家人身边走失
Earlier tonight, he ran away from his family.
他的家人只希望能把他送回活人的世界
They just want to send him back to the Land of the Living.
等等等等
Wait, wait, wait.
你说歌神是你唯一的家人
You said de la Cruz was your only family.
只有他才能送你回家
The only person who could send you home.
我是有其他的家人
I do have other family, but...
你早就可以带着我的照片回去了
You could have taken my photo back this whole time?
但是他们讨厌音乐 我需要音乐家的祝福
But they hate music. I need a musician's blessing.
- 你骗了我 - 噢 你还好意思说我
- You lied to me! - Oh, you're one to talk.
你看着我 我就要被人遗忘了 米格
Look at me, I'm being forgotten, Miguel.
我不知道我能不能撑过今晚
I don't even know if I'm gonna last the night.
我绝不能错过眼前的这个过桥的好机会
I'm not gonna miss my one chance to cross that bridge
让你去追求什么荒唐可笑的音乐梦
'cause you want to live out some stupid musical fantasy.
一点也不可笑 跟我去找你的家人
- It's not stupid. - I'm taking you to your family.
放开我 一会儿你就会感谢我了
- Let go of me. - You'll thank me later.
你根本不想帮我 你只想着你自己
You don't wanna help me. You only care about yourself.
你的照片还给你 不行
Keep your dumb photo. - No!
不不不 别跟着我了
No, no, no! - Stay away from me!
不
No!
嗨 小格格?
Hey, chamaco?
你去哪儿?
Where did you go?
小格格?
Chamaco?
对不起
Sorry!
快回来!
Come back.
丹丹 别叫好不好
Dante, cállate.
别叫了丹丹 别这样
Don't Dante, stop it.
他帮不了我
He can't help me.
丹丹 行了
Dante, stop.
别管我
Stop it.
别烦我了
Leave me alone!
你根本不是埃伯瑞吉 你就是一只土狗
You're not a spirit guide, you're just a dumb dog.
你给我走开!
Now get outta here!
是他!
It's him!
是那个活人小男孩!
It's that living boy!
我刚刚听到他说话了!快看!
I've heard about him, look!
他是活人
He's alive.
别胡闹了 小格!
This nonsense ends now, Miguel!
我现在就把祝福给你 然后你立刻回家
I am giving you my blessing, and you are going home.
我不要你的祝福!
I don't want your blessing.
米格 站住!
Miguel! Stop!
回来!
Come back!
小格!
Miguel!
我这是在救你的命
I am trying to save your life.
你是在要我的命!
You're ruining my life.
什么?
What?
没有音乐我就活的不开心
Music's the only thing that makes me happy.
可你们 你们就是不让我玩
A-and you... you wanna take that away.
你们永远都不明白
You'll never understand.
就算要我付出生命
♪ Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona ♪
我也无法停止爱你
♪ No dejaré de quererte ♪
我以为您讨厌音乐
I-I thought you hated music.
噢 我喜欢音乐
Oh, I loved it.
我还记得那种感觉
I remember that feeling.
我丈夫在我身边弹吉他 我在他旁边唱歌
When my husband would play, and I would sing.
其他的一切都不重要了
And nothing else mattered.
但后来我们有了可可
But when we had Coco...
就在一瞬间 我感觉我的生命里有比音乐更重要的东西
suddenly, there was something in my life that mattered more than music.
我当时一心想安定下来
I wanted to put down rules.
可他却想唱遍全世界
He wanted to play for the world.
为自己想要的生活 我们不得不做出牺牲
We each made a sacrifice to get what we wanted.
现在 你也要做出选择
Now, you must make a choice.
但是我不想做这样的选择
But I don't wanna pick sides.
你们为什么不支持我呢?
Why can't you be on my side?
一家人难道不应该
That's what family's supposed to do.
互相支持吗?
Support you.
但是你们永远都不会
But you never will.
祝你们玩得高兴
Have a good time.
天呐 我太激动了
Oh, how exciting!
嗨 亚利桑多先生!
Oh, El Santo!
我 我是您的粉丝
I-I-I'm a big fan.
您能不能让我?
You mind if I?
谢谢您 先生
Gracias, señor.
入场券呢?
Invitation?
用不着 我是歌神德拉库斯的曾曾孙子
It's okay, I'm Ernesto's great-great-grandson.
对不起 打扰了
Disculpe, señores.
嗨嗨 你们看 这是那首有点疯狂
Hey, hey, guys, it's Poco Loco!
你今晚的表现实在是太精彩了
You were on fire tonight.
你们也是
You too!
看在同行的份上 帮我一个忙吧
Hey, musician to musician, I need a favor.
音乐大赛的冠军 祝贺你们 请进
Oh, the competition winners. Congratulations, chicos.
多谢各位
Thanks guys.
嘿 好好玩吧 音乐小王子 谢谢啦
- Hey, enjoy the party, little músico. - Gracias.
快看 歌神在那儿
Look, it's Ernesto.
德拉库斯
De la Cruz.
歌神德拉库斯
Señor de la Cruz!
不好意思
Pardon me.
德拉库斯先生!
Señor de la Cruz!
德拉库斯!
Señor de la...
遇到好机会 绝不能轻易放过
When you see your moment, you mustn't let it pass you by.
一定要抓住机会
You must seize it.
我们就快到了
We're almost there, Dante.
德拉库斯先生
Señor de la Cruz!
德拉库斯
Señor de la...
我们要怎么办呢 这毫无希望
But what can we do? It is hopeless.
你要有信心 修女
You must have faith, sister.
可是神父 他是不会听我的
Oh, but Padre, he will never listen.
那就用音乐来说服他
He will listen to music.
女士们 先生们
♪ Señoras y señores ♪
各位午安 各位晚安
♪ Buenas tardes Buenas noches ♪
女士们 先生们
♪ Señoritas y señores ♪
今晚我们齐聚一堂
♪ To be here with you tonight ♪
带给你满心欢喜
♪ Brings me joy, Que alegría ♪
我用音乐代替音乐
♪ For this music is my language ♪
这世界是个大家庭
♪ And the world es mi familia ♪
我用音乐代替言语
♪ For this music is my language ♪
这世界是个大家庭
♪ And the world es mi familia ♪
我用音乐代替言语
♪ For this music is my language ♪
这世界是个大家庭
♪ And the woo-orld es mi familia ♪
我用音乐代替言语
♪ For this music is my Lang-
啊!
Ah!
你没事吧?小伙子
Are you all right, niño?
是 是你?
It-it's you.
你就是那个男孩儿?
Y-you are that boy.
那个从活人世界里来的那个孩子?
The one who came from the Land of the Living.
你 你知道我?
You... know about me?
今晚大家说来说去说的都是你
You're all anyone has been talking about.
你怎么到这儿来了?
Why have you come here?
我是米格
I'm Miguel.
我是您的曾曽孙子
Your g-great-great-grandson.
我还有个曾曾孙子?
I have a great-great-grandson?
我需要您的祝福
I need your blessing.
所以我回家后就能像您一样成为一名音乐家
So I can go back home and be a musician just like you.
家里的其他人
The rest of our family...
都不停我说
they wouldn't listen.
但是我希望您会听
But I... I hoped you would.
我的孩子 你有这样的才华
My boy, with a talent like yours...
我怎么会不听呢?
how could I not listen?
我有了一个曾曾孙子!
Haha! I have a great-great-grandson!
快看! 弗里达
Look, it's Frida!
对啊 弗里达·卡罗
Yes, it is I, Frida Kahlo.
这是我的荣幸 夫人
It is an honor, señora.
谢谢
Gracias.
嗨 内格雷特 因凡特
Hey, Negrete, Infante.
见过我的曾曾孙子没有?
Have you met my great-great-grandson?
这是我的曾曾孙子!
My great-great-grandson!
他还活着 他还是个小小音乐家
He is alive and a musician, to boot.
有酒窝 没酒窝 有酒窝 没酒窝
Dimple, no dimple. Dimple, no dimple.
没酒窝!
No dimple!
为我们的友谊干杯!
To our friendship. Haha!
我会为你披荆斩棘 擦枪走火 干杯!
I'd move heaven and earth for you, mi amigo. Salud!
有毒!
Poison!
你知道吗?我从不用替身
You know, I did all my own stunts.
虽然再见必须说 请记住我
♪ Though I have to say goodbye Remember me ♪
这里的一切都是活人世界里我的歌迷们送的
All of this came from my amazing fans in the Land of the Living.
他们送的太多了 我都不知道该怎么办了
They leave me more offerings than I know what to do with.
嘿 怎么了
Hey, what's wrong?
是事情太多了吗?你看起来有些迷茫
Is it too much? You look overwhelmed.
不 这些都很好
N-no, It's all great.
那你是?只是...
- But? - It's just...
我从小到大一直崇拜你
I've been looking up to you my whole life.
你是那个真正成功了的人
You're the guy who actually did it.
可是你有后悔过吗?
But did you ever regret it?
为了音乐放弃了所有东西?
Choosing music over everything else?
离开家乡是很艰难
It was hard saying goodbye to my hometown.
独自一人上路
Heading off on my own.
离开你的家人?
Leaving your family?
是的
Si.
但是再给我一次机会我也不会有别的选择
But I could not have done it differently.
谁都不能违背命运的安排
One cannot deny who one is meant to be.
而你 我的曾曾孙子...
And you, my great-great-grandson...
命中注定要成为一个音乐家
are meant to be a musician.
你和我 我们是艺术家 米格
You and I, we are artists, Miguel.
才华不能埋没在小家里
We cannot belong to one family.
外面的世界才是我们的家!
The world is our family!
哦!哦!开始放烟花了!
Ooh-hoo! Ooh! The fireworks have begun!
很快 大家就会去我的演唱会狂欢了
Soon, the party will move across town for my sunrise spectacular.
哈!米格 你一定要来看表演啊!
Hunh! Miguel, you must come to the show!
你可以做我的特邀嘉宾
You will be my guest of honor.
真的吗?当然了孩子
- You mean it? - Of course, my boy.
我不能去
I can't.
我必须要在天亮之前回到家
I have to get home before sunrise.
嚯!确实得让你回家了
Oy! I really do need to get you home.
这也是我的荣幸
It has been an honor.
真不想把你送走 米格
I am sorry to see you go, Miguel.
希望你尽快死去
I hope you die very soon.
你知道我是什么意思
You know what I mean.
米格...
Miguel...
给你我的祝福
I give you my blessing.
我们说好了的 小子
We had a deal, chamaco.
你是谁?这是什么意思?
Who are you? What is the meaning of this?
哦 弗里达 我还以为你不来了
Oh, Frida. I thought you couldn't make it.
你说过你会把我的照片带回去的
You said you'd take back my photo.
你答应过的 米格!
You promised, Miguel.
你认识这个人?
You know this uh, man?
今天晚上刚认识的
I just met him tonight.
他说我他认识你
He told me he knew you.
赫...埃克托?
H...Héctor?
求你了 米格
Please, Miguel.
把我的照片挂起来吧
Put my photo up.
我的朋友 你要... 要被人遗忘了
My friend. You're... you're being forgotten.
那又是谁的错呢?
And whose fault is that?
埃克托 拜托 你拿走的是我的歌
- Héctor, please. - Those were my songs you took.
是我的歌让你成名的
My songs that made you famous.
什么?如果我被人遗忘了...
- What? - If I'm being forgotten...
就是因为 你没有告诉别人 这些歌是我写的
It's because you never told anyone that I wrote them.
你胡说 德拉库斯的歌都是他自己写的
That's crazy. De la Cruz wrote all his own songs.
你要告诉他吗?或者我来说?
You wanna tell him? Or should I?
埃克托 我从没想过占取你的功劳
Héctor, I never meant to take credit.
我们合作的很好 但是...
We made a great team, but...
你去世了 并且... 我唱你的歌是因为
you died, and... I-I only sang your songs because
我想让你的生命以这种方式延续下去
I wanted to keep a part of you alive.
哦!还真是好心啊!
Oh, how generous!
你们以前真的是搭档啊
You really did play together.
听着 我不想跟你争这个
Look, I don't want to fight about it.
我只想让你做点弥补
I just want you to make it right.
米格可以挂起我的照片
Miguel can put my photo up.
埃克托 然后我就能过桥
- Héctor. - And I can cross over the bridge.
见到我的女儿了
I could see my girl.
埃克托
Ernesto.
你还记得我离开的那天晚上吗?
Remember the night I left?
已经过去很久了
That was a long time ago.
我们一起喝酒
We drank together.
你告诉我你会为了你的朋友赴汤蹈火
And you told me you would move heaven and earth for your amigo.
那么 我现在求你帮帮我
Well, I'm asking you to now.
赴汤蹈火?
Heaven and earth?
像电影里一样吗?
Like in the movie?
什么?
What?
那是伊达尔戈先生的祝酒词
That's Don Hidalgo's toast.
在德拉库斯的电影《回家的路》里
In the de la Cruz movie, "El Camino a Casa."
我说的是我自己 米格
I'm talking about my real life, Miguel.
不 电影里也有
No, it's in there.
看!
Look!
值得喝一杯
This calls for a toast.
敬我们的友谊!哈哈!
To our friendship! Haha!
我会为你赴汤蹈火的 朋友
I would move heaven and earth for you, mi amigo.
但是在电影里 伊达尔戈先生在酒里下毒了
But in the movie, Don Hidalgo poisons the drink.
干杯
Salud.
有毒!
Poison!
那天晚上 埃克托
That night, Ernesto.
我离开的那天晚上
The night I left.
我们已经在外面演出好几个月了
We've been performing on the road for months.
我突然很想家 所以我收拾了东西
I got homesick and I packed up my songs.
你要现在放弃?
You wanna give up now?
在差一点就要实现我们的梦想的时候?
When we're this close to reaching our dream?
这是你的梦想 你自己搞定
This was your dream. You'll manage.
没有你的歌我做不到 埃克托
I can't do this without your songs, Héctor.
我要回家了 埃克托
I'm going home, Ernesto.
尽管恨我吧 但是我下定决心了
Hate me if you want. But my mind is made up.
哦 我不会恨你的
Oh, I could never hate you.
如果你一定要走 那... 让我举杯为你送行
If you must go, then I'm... I'm sending you off with a toast.
敬我们的友谊
To our friendship.
我会为你赴汤蹈火的 朋友
I would move heaven and earth for you, mi amigo.
干杯!
Salud!
你送我去火车站
You walked me to the train station.
但是我肚子特别痛
But I felt a pain in my stomach.
我以为是吃的东西出了问题
I thought it must have been something I ate.
也许是吃的香肠坏了 伙计
Perhaps it was that chorizo, my friend.
原来是我喝的东西有问题
Or something I drank.
我就这样死了
I woke up dead.
你...
You...
毒死了我!
poisoned me!
你把电影和现实混为一谈了 埃克托
You're confusing movies with reality, Héctor.
这么长时间 我以为只是运气不好
All this time, I thought it was just bad luck.
我从没想过你竟然...
I never thought that you might have...
竟然...
that you...
你怎么能这样做?
How could you?
埃克托!
Héctor!
警卫!警卫!
Security! Security!
你夺走了我的一切!
You took everything away from me!
你这个卑鄙的小人!
You rat!
照顾好他
Have him taken care of.
他状态不太好
He's not well.
我只是想回家!
I just wanted to move back home!
不!不!
No! No!
对不起
I apologize.
我们说到哪了?
Where were we?
你说你会祝福我
You were going to give me your blessing.
是的...呃...是
Yes... ah... Si.
米格...
Miguel...
我的个人名誉...
My reputation... it is...
对我非常重要
very important to me.
我不想让你觉得..
I would hate to have you think...
觉得你为了得到埃克托的歌而谋杀了他?
That you m-murdered Héctor for his songs?
你不是这样想的吧
You don't think that.
是吗?
Do you?
我... 不... 大家都知道你是...是好人
I... No... Everyone knows you're the... the good guy.
德拉库斯爷爷... 你还给我你的祝福吗?
Papá Ernesto... my blessing?
警卫?
Security?
照顾好米格 他暂时不回去了
Take care of Miguel. He'll be extending his stay.
什么?
What?
我可是你的家人啊!
But I'm your family!
埃克托还是我最好的朋友呢
And Héctor was my best friend.
成功是要付出代价的 米格
Success doesn't come for free, Miguel.
你必须不惜一切代价去...
You have to be willing to do whatever it takes to...
抓住机会
seize your moment.
我知道你会懂的
I know you understand.
不! 不!
No! No!
放开我!
Let go!
不!
No!
啊哈!
Aah!
救命啊!
Help!
有人能听见吗?
Can anyone hear me?
我想回家!
I wanna go home!
哈?
Huh?
赫 埃克托?
H-Héctor?
孩子?哦 埃克托!
- Kid? - Oh, Héctor!
你是对的
You were right.
我应该回到我家人身边的
I should have gone back to my family.
嘿 嘿 嘿 他们告诉我不要像德拉库斯一样
- Hey, hey, hey. - They told me not to be like de la Cruz.
但是我没有听 嘿 没有关系的
- But I didn't listen. - Hey, it's okay.
我还说我不在意人们是否会记住我
But I told them I didn't care if they remembered me.
我还说我不在乎照片是不是能上灵坛
I didn't care if was on the stupid ofrenda.
嘿 臭小子 没关系的
Hey, chamaco, it's okay.
没关系的
It's okay.
我告诉他们我不在意
I told them I didn't care.
哈?不! 埃克托!
- Huh! Oh! - Héctor!
埃克托!
Héctor?
她...
She's...
她快把我忘了...
forgetting me.
谁?
Who?
我的女儿
My daughter.
所以你那么想过桥就是为了她
She's the reason you wanted to cross the bridge.
我只是想再次见到她
I just wanted to see her again.
我不应该离开塞西莉娅的
I never should have left Santa Cecilia.
真希望我能给她道歉
I wish I could apologize.
真希望我能告诉她她的爸爸在想办法回家
I wish I could tell her that her Papá was trying to come home.
爸爸非常爱她
That he loved her so much.
我的可可
My Coco.
可可?
Coco?
你是
Where?
你是在哪拿到这个的?
Where did you get this?
这是我曾奶奶可可
That's my Mamá Coco.
这是我曾曾奶奶伊梅尔达
That's my Mamá Imelda.
这是...
Is that...
你?
You?
我们是...
We're...
一家人?
- family? - Family?
我一直希望能再见到她
I always hoped I'd see her again.
希望她会想我
That she'd miss me.
为我布置灵坛
Maybe put up my photo.
但是她没有
But it never happened.
你知道最糟糕的是什么吗?
You know the worst part?
即使我永远不会再活的世界见到可可
Even if I never got to see Coco in the living world...
将来总有一天她也会来到这
I thought at least one day, I'd see her here.
我一定要好好抱抱她
Give her the biggest hug.
但是她是最后一个记住我的人
But she's the last person who remembers me.
她离开活人的世界的那一瞬间...
The moment she's gone from the living world...
你就会
You disappear.
从这个世界消失
From this one.
你将永远都不会见到她了
You'll never get to see her.
永远见不到了
Ever again.
你知道...
You know...
我有一次给她写了首歌
I wrote her a song once.
我们以前每天晚上
We used to sing it every night.
都会唱这首歌
At the same time.
不管我们相距多远
No matter how far apart we were.
我多想再给她唱一次
What I wouldn't give to sing it to her.
就唱
One...
最后
last...
一次
time.
请记住我
♪ Remember me ♪
虽然再见必须说
♪ Though I have to say goodbye ♪
请记住我
♪ Remember me ♪
眼泪不要坠落
♪ Don't let it make you cry ♪
我虽然要离你远去
♪ For even if I'm far away ♪
你住在我心里
♪ I hold you in my heart ♪
在每个分离的夜里
♪ I sing a secret song to you ♪
为你唱一首歌
♪ Each night we are apart ♪
请记住我
♪ Remember me ♪
爸爸!
Papá!
虽然我要去远方
♪ Though I have to travel far ♪
请记住我
♪ Remember me ♪
当听见吉他的悲伤
♪ Each time you hear a sad guitar ♪
这是我跟你在一起
♪ Know that I'm with you ♪
唯一的凭据
♪ The only way that I can be ♪
直到我再次拥抱你
♪ Until you're in my arms again ♪
请记住
♪ Remember ♪
我
♪ Me ♪
他...他偷走了你的吉他
H-He stole your guitar.
他偷走了你的歌
He stole your songs.
你才应该被世人铭记
You should be the one the world remembers.
不是德拉库斯
Not de la Cruz.
"请记住我"并不是写给全世界的
I didn't write "Remember Me" for the world.
是写给可可的
I wrote it for Coco.
我真不配做你的曾曾爷爷
I'm a pretty sorry excuse for a great-great-grandpa.
你在开玩笑吗?刚才我还以为我杀人犯是我的家人
Are you kidding? A minute ago, I thought I was related to a murderer.
你比他好太多了
You're a total upgrade.
从小到大
My whole life...
我和家里的人就是不一样
there's been something that made me different.
可是我从来都不知道为什么
And I never knew where it came from.
但是现在我知道了
But now, I know.
是因为你!
It comes from you!
我们是一家人 我很骄傲
I'm proud we're family.
我们是一家人太好了!
I'm proud to be his family!
丹丹?
Dante?
Dante!
是丹丹!
It's Dante!
哈哈!
Haha!
伊梅尔达!
Imelda!
埃克托
Héctor.
你看起来不错
You look good.
丹丹!
Dante!
你知道他是我的曾曾爷爷埃克托!
You knew he was my Papá Héctor the whole time!
你真是一条聪明的狗
You are a real spirit guide.
谁是最好的狗?是你!
Who's a good spirit guide? You are!
丹丹!
Dante!
他们在这!
There they are!
米格利托!米格利托!
Miguelito! Miguelito!
谢谢
Gracias, Dios mio!
我担心死了
Mijo, I was so worried.
还好我们及时找到你了
Thank goodness we found you in time.
至于你
And you.
我还要赶走你多少次?
How many times must I turn you away?
伊梅尔达
Imelda...
我不想和你有任何关系 活着没有 死了更别想
I want nothing to do with you. Not in life, not in death.
我花了几十年让我的子孙远离你当年犯的错误
I spent decades protecting my family from your mistakes.
他只跟你一起呆了五分钟 我就得把他从污水坑里捞出来!
He spends five minutes with you, and I have to fish him out of a sinkhole!
不是埃克托的错
I wasn't in there 'cause of Héctor.
他是因为我才在那里的
He was in there 'cause of me.
他只是想帮我回家
He was just trying to get me home.
是我不听话
I didn't wanna listen.
但是他是对的
But he was right.
没有什么比家人更重要了
Nothing is more important than family.
我已经准备好接受您的祝福了
I'm ready to accept your blessing.
什么条件都答应
And your conditions.
不过我们先要找到德拉库斯
But first, I need to find de la Cruz.
拿回埃克托的照片
To get Héctor's photo.
什么?这样他就可以在此看到可可了
- What? - So he can see Coco again.
家里的灵坛上应该有他
Héctor should be on our ofrenda.
他也是这个家庭的一员
He's part of our family.
他离开了他的家庭
He left this family.
他一直想办法回到你和可可身边
He tried to go home to you and Coco.
但是德拉库斯害死了他
But de la Cruz murdered him.
是真的
It's true, Imelda.
是真的又怎样?
And so what if it's true?
你抛弃了我 让我独自抚养孩子
You leave me alone with a child to raise,
难道我应该原谅你吗
and I'm just supposed to forgive you?
伊梅尔达 我...
Imelda, I...
埃克托?
Héctor?
哈!
Hunh!
我没有时间了
I'm running out of time.
是可可
It's Coco.
因为她快把你忘了
She's forgetting you.
你可以不用原谅他
You don't have to forgive him.
但是 我们不该忘了他
But we shouldn't forget him.
我真的很想把你忘了
I wanted to forget you.
我还想可可也把你忘了 但是...
I wanted Coco to forget you too, but...
都是我的错
This is my fault.
不怪你
Not yours.
对不起 伊梅尔达
I'm sorry, Imelda.
米格...
Miguel...
如果我们帮你拿回他的照片...
If we help you get his photo...
你就答应我们回家去
you will return home.
不再碰音乐
No more music.
家人永远最重要
Family comes first.
我...我真的无法原谅你
I... I can't forgive you.
但我还是会帮助你
But I will help you.
我们怎样才能接近德拉库斯?
So how do we get to de la Cruz?
我知道一个办法或许可以
I might know a way.
祝你们好运 孩子们
Good luck, muchacho.
谢谢 弗里达
Gracias, Frida.
啊!
Ah!
来 让我帮你...
Here, let me help you with...
别碰我
Don't touch me.
大家都清楚计划了吧?
Everyone clear on the plan?
找到埃克托的照片
Find Héctor's photo.
拿给米格
Give it to Miguel.
送米格回家
Send Miguel home.
都有花瓣了吗?
Got your petals?
现在 我们只要找到德拉库斯就行了
Now, we just have to find de la Cruz.
- 谁找我? - 啊!
- Yes? - Ah!
我好像不认识你吧?
Don't I know you?
这一下是教训你谋杀了我一生最爱的人!
That's for murdering the love of my life!
- 你说谁? - 她说的是我
- Who the? - She's talking about me.
我是你一生最爱的人?
I'm the love your your life?
别打岔 我还生着气呢
I don't know, I'm still angry at you.
埃克托?你怎么...
Héctor? How did you...
这一下是教训你差点害死了我的孙子!
And that's for trying to murder my grandson!
- 你孙子? - 她说的是我
- Grandson? - She's talking about me.
是你!
You!
等下 你和埃克托是什么一家人?
Wait. You're related to Héctor?
照片!
The photo!
呃...
Eh...
追上他!
After him!
保安 快救我
Security, ayuda.
你说我是你一生最爱的人?
You said love of your life?
谁知道我刚才说了什么
I don't know what I said.
我可听到了
That's what I heard.
德拉库斯先生 还有30秒才到您上台呢
Places, señor. You're on in 30 seconds.
米格 我拿到了!
Miguel, I have it!
哦!
Oh!
快点 上去!
Hurry, come on!
女士们先生们!
Ladies and gentleman!
欢迎伟大的德拉库斯登场!
The one. The only. Ernesto de la Cruz!
快把她抓下来!
Get her off the stage!
唱啊!
Sing!
唉
♪ Ay ♪
♫ 啊 哭泣的女人 ♫
♪ de mí, Llorona ♪
♫ 像雨天一样悲伤 ♫
♪ Llorona de azul Celeste ♪
♫ 啊 哭泣的女人 ♫
♪ Ay de mí, Llorona ♪
♫ 像雨天一样悲伤 ♫
♪ Llorona de azul Celeste ♪
♫ 就算让我付出生命 ♫
♪ Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona ♪
♫ 我也无法停止爱你 ♫
♪ No dejaré de quererte ♪
♫ 无法停止爱你 ♫
♫ 我爬上松林之巅 ♫
♪ Me subí Al pino más alto, Llorona ♪
♫ 只为寻你踪影 ♫
♪ A ver Si Te divisaba ♪
♫ 摇落的露水 ♫
♪ Como El pino era tierno, Llorona ♪
♫ 仿佛我的眼泪 ♫
♪ Al verme llorar, lloraba ♪
♫ 啊 哭泣的女人 ♫
♪ Ay de mí, Llorona, Llorona ♪
♫ 像雨天一样悲伤 ♫
♪ Llorona de azul Celeste ♪
♫ 啊 哭泣的女人 ♫
♪ Ay de mí, Llorona, Llorona ♪
♫ 像雨天一样悲伤 ♫
♪ Llorona de azul Celeste ♪
♫ 就算让我付出生命 ♫
♪ Y aunque la vida me cueste, Llorona ♪
♫ 我也无法停止爱你 ♫
♪ No dejaré de quererte ♪
♫ 就算让我付出生命 ♫ 放开我!
♪ Y aunque la vida me cueste ♪ - Let go of me!
♫ 哭泣的女人 ♫
♪ Llorona ♪
♫ 我也无法停止爱你 ♫
♪ No dejaré de quererte ♪
唉 唉 唉!
♪ ¡Ay, ay, ay! ♪
我都快忘记唱歌的感觉了
I forgot what that felt like.
你...唱的还是这么好
You... still got it.
咳咳...
Uh-h-hum...
哦!
Oh!
米格 我把祝福送给你...
Miguel, I give you my blessing...
让你回家...
To go home...
把我们的照片摆上灵台...
To put up our photos...
并且永远别...
And to never...
永远别碰音乐
Never play music again.
永远别忘了你的家人们有多爱你
To never forget how much your family loves you.
你要回家啦
You're going home.
你哪儿也别想去!
You're not going anywhere!
伊梅尔达!
Imelda!
别过来!别过来!
Stay back! Stay back!
所有人 都别过来!
All of you, stay back!
不准再靠近一步
Not one more step.
丹丹!
Dante!
住手 德拉库斯!
Ernesto, stop!
放了那个男孩儿
Leave the boy alone.
我也很不容易 埃克托
I've worked too hard, Héctor.
不能让他毁了我的一切
Too hard to let him destroy everything.
他只是个孩子 德拉库斯
He's a living child, Ernesto.
他是个威胁
He's a threat.
你以为我会让他带着你的照片 回到活人的世界?
You think I'd let him go back to the Land of the Living with your photo?
让大家又记起你吗?
To keep your memory alive?
- 不 - 你是个懦夫!
- No. - You're a coward!
我是歌神德拉库斯 史上最伟大的音乐家
I am Ernesto de la Cruz. The greatest musician of all time.
埃克托才是最伟大的音乐家
Héctor's the real musician.
你谋杀了他 还偷走了他的歌
You're just the guy who murdered him and stole his songs.
谋杀?
Murdered?
那是我为了抓住机会
I am the one who's willing to do what it takes
而不择手段
to seize my moment.
不惜一切代价
Whatever it takes.
啊!啊!
Aah! Aah!
不!
No!
- 米格!- 米格!
- Miguel! - Miguel!
抱歉了 老朋友 表演还得继续呢
Apologies, old friend. But the show must go on.
哈哈!
Haha!
呸!呸!
Boo! Boo!
呸!
Boo!
哈哈哈 抱歉 抱歉 我的家人们!
Hahaha! Please, please, mi familia!
- 杀人犯! - 快滚下台去!
- Murderer! - Get off the stage!
乐队准备 一二一...
Orchestra, a-one, a-two, a-one...
♫ 请记住我 ♫
♪ Remember me ♪
♫ 虽然再见必... ♫
♪ Though I have to s- ♪
卑鄙小人!
Hey, creep!
快看!
Look!
小猫咪
Nice kitty.
啊!
Ah!
快把我放下来!
Put me down!
拜托!
Please!
求你了!停下 快停下!
I'm begging you! Stop, stop!
啊!
Aaah!
啊!啊哈!
Aah! Aaah!
喔!
Oooh!
噢!不!
Oh! No!
啊!
Aaah!
哈!
Hunh!
我错过了什么?
What did I miss?
好狗狗 丹丹
Good boy, Dante.
米格!
Miguel!
哦!
Oh!
埃克托!
Héctor!
照片 我弄丢了
The photo, I lost it.
没关系 孩子
It's okay, mijo.
没关...
It's...
埃克托!
Héctor!
埃克托?
Héctor?
可可
Coco.
不 我们还能找回照片
No, we can still find the photo.
米格 天快亮了
Miguel, it's almost sunrise.
不 不 不 我不还能走
No, no, no. I can't leave you.
我答应过你要把你的照片带回去
I promised I put your photo up.
让你能见到可可太奶奶
I promised you'd see Coco.
我们都快没时间了 孩子
We're both out of time, mijo.
不!不!
No! No!
她不能就这么把你忘了
She can't forget you.
我只是想让她知道...
I just wanted her to know...
爸爸一直都很爱她
that I loved her.
埃克托!
Héctor!
我们把祝福送给你 米格
You have our blessing, Miguel.
没有任何条件
No conditions.
不 埃克托曾曾爷爷 求你了
No, Papá Héctor. Please!
不
No.
回家吧
Go home.
我保证!我一定不会让可可太奶奶忘了你的!
I promise! I-I won't let Coco forget you!
他在那儿!
There he is!
米格!站住!
Miguel! Stop!
你去哪儿了?
Where have you been?
啊!我要见可可太奶奶 求你了!
Ah! I need to see Mamá Coco, please!
啊!你拿着那把吉他做什么?
Huh! What are you doing with that?
把它给我!
Give it to me!
米格 站住
Miguel, stop.
米格!米格?
Miguel! Miguel?
米格!
Miguel!
可可太奶奶?
Mamá Coco?
能听到我吗?
Can you hear me?
我是米格
It's Miguel.
我见到您爸爸了!
I-I saw your Papá!
还记得他吗?爸爸?
Remember? Papá?
求您了
Please.
如果您忘了他
If you forget him.
他就再也回不来了
He'll be gone.
永远消失
Forever.
看 这是他的吉他 还记得吗?
Here. This was his guitar, right?
他以前经常弹给您听
He used to play it to you?
看 这个就是他
See, there he is.
爸爸 记得吗?爸爸?
Papá, remember? Papá?
米格!
Miguel!
太奶奶 求您了 不要忘了他
Mamá Coco, please. Don't forget him.
你急着找太奶奶干什么?
What are you doing to that poor woman?
没事了 妈妈
It's okay, mother.
你这孩子是怎么回事?
What's gotten into you?
我以为你丢了 米格
I thought I lost you, Miguel.
对不起 爸爸
I'm sorry, Papá.
一家人又在一起了
We're all together now.
这才是最重要的
That's what matters.
还差一个人
Not all of us.
没事了 妈妈
It's okay, Mamita.
米格 快来向太奶奶道歉
Miguel, you apologize to your Mamá Coco.
太奶奶...
Mamá Coco...
快 道歉
Well, apologize.
太奶奶...
Mamá Coco...
您的爸爸...
Your Papá...
他想让您听听这首歌
He wanted you to have this.
妈妈 等一下...
Mamá... wait...
♫ 请记住我 ♫
♪ Remember me ♪
♫ 虽然再见必须说 ♫
♪ Though I have to say goodbye ♪
♫ 请记住我 ♫
♪ Remember me ♪
♫ 眼泪不要坠落 ♫
♪ Don't let it make you cry ♪
♫ 我虽然要离你远去 ♫ 你们看!
♪ For even if I'm far away ♪ - Look!
♫ 你住在我心底 ♫
♪ I hold you in my heart ♪
♫ 在每个分离的夜里 ♫
♪ I sing a secret song to you ♪
♫ 为你唱一首歌 ♫
♪ Each night we are apart ♪
♫ 请记住我 ♫
♪ Remember me ♪
♫ 虽然我要去远方 ♫
♪ Though I have to travel far ♪
♫ 请记住我 ♫
♪ Remember me ♪
♫ 当听见吉他的悲伤 ♫
♪ Each time you hear a sad guitar ♪
♫ 这是我跟你在一起 ♫
♪ Know that I'm with you ♪
♫ 唯一的凭据 ♫
♪ The only way that I can be ♪
♫ 直到我再次拥抱你 ♫
♪ Until you're in my arms again ♪
♫ 请记住 ♫
♪ Remember ♪
♫ 我 ♫
♪ Me ♪
埃琳娜?
Elena?
你怎么了 孩子?
What's wrong, mija?
没事 妈妈
Nothing, Mamá.
就是太高兴了
Nothing at all.
我爸爸过去一直都唱这首歌
My Papá used to sing me that song.
他一直爱您 太奶奶
He loved you, Mamá Coco.
您的爸爸非常爱您
Your Papá loved you so much.
我一直留着他写的信
I kept his letters.
里面有写给我的诗
Poems he wrote me.
还有...
And...
我的爸爸是个音乐家
Papá was a musician.
在我还是个小女孩的时候...
When I was a little girl...
他和妈妈会一起唱非常动听的歌
He and Mamá would sing such beautiful songs.
一年后
One year later
请记住我
Remember me
鬼才记住你
Forgotten.
请看这里
And right over here,
这是圣塞西莉亚伟大的文化瑰宝之一
one of Santa Cecilia's greatest treasures.
著名的词曲家海特曾经在这里生活
The home of the esteemed songwriter, Héctor Rivera.
在他写给女儿可可的一封封家书中
The letters Héctor wrote home for his daughter, Coco
可以看到许多流传于世的佳作
contain the lyrics for all of your favorite songs.
包括《请记住我》
Not just "Remember Me."
这是胡里奥太爷爷
And that man is your Papá Julio.
这是罗西塔姨奶奶
And there's Tía Rosita.
这是维多利亚姨奶奶
And your Tía Victoria.
那是奥斯卡和费利佩舅爷爷
And those two are Oscar and Felipe.
照片里的人都是我们的家人
There aren't just old pictures, they're our family.
我们永远都不能忘记他们
And they're counting on us to remember them.
♫ 你叫我疯子 ♫ 下一位
♪ Say that I'm crazy ♪ - Next.
♫ 我傻得可以 ♫
♪ Or call me a fool ♪
祝你探亲愉快 埃克托
Enjoy your visit, Héctor.
♫ 但昨夜梦里我仿佛看见你 ♫
♪ But last night it seemed that I dreamed about you ♪
爸爸!
Papá!
可可!
Coco!
♫ 当我开口要说 言语变一首歌 ♫
♪ And you knew every word ♪
♫ 每一句都熟悉 我们来一起唱 ♫
♪ And we all sang along ♪
♫ 旋律华丽响起 ♫
♪ To a melody played ♪
♫ 灵魂在音符里 ♫
♪ On the strings of our souls  ♪
♫ 我们身体摆动 ♫
♪ And a rhythm that rattled us ♪
♫ 跟着音乐节奏 ♫
♪ Down to the bone ♪
♫ 我们相亲相爱 ♫
♪ Our love for each other ♪
♫ 生命不灭不熄 ♫
♪ Will live on forever ♪
♫ 我的心跳 ♫
♪ In every beat ♪
♫ 全都充满自豪 ♫
♪ Of my proud corazón ♪
♫ 我们相亲相爱 ♫
♪ Our love for each other ♪
♫ 生命不灭不熄 ♫
♪ Will live on forever ♪
♫ 我的心跳 ♫
♪ In every beat ♪
♫ 全都充满自豪 ♫
♪ Of my proud corazón ♪
♫ 我的大家庭 ♫
♪ Ay mi familia ♪
♫ 我的好朋友 ♫
♪ Oiga mi gente ♪
♫ 你可感觉到 ♫
♪ Canten a coro ♪
♫ 你可知道 ♫
♪ Let it be known ♪
♫ 我们相亲相爱 ♫
♪ Our love for each other ♪
♫ 生命不灭不熄 ♫
♪ Will live on forever ♪
♫ 我的心跳 ♫
♪ In every beat ♪
♫ 全都充满自豪 ♫
♪ Of my proud corazón ♪
♫ 我的大家庭 ♫
♪ Ay mi familia ♪
♫ 我的好朋友 ♫
♪ Oiga mi gente ♪
♫ 你可感觉到 ♫
♪ Canten a coro ♪
♫ 你可知道 ♫
♪ Let it be known ♪
♫ 我们相亲相爱 ♫
♪ Our love for each other ♪
♫ 生命不灭不熄 ♫
♪ Will live on forever ♪
♫ 我的心跳 ♫
♪ In every beat ♪
♫ 全都充满自豪 ♫
♪ Of my proud corazón ♪